Guide to the Records of Ad Hoc Committee on the Human Rights and Genocide Treaties WAG.037
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Ad Hoc Committee on the Human Rights and Genocide Treaties Records
Bulk, 1960-1979
1943-1984
WAG.037
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
6.0 linear feet (6 boxes)
The Ad Committee on the Human Rights and Genocide Treaties was organized in the spring of 1964 by some 35 national voluntary organizations for the purpose of encouraging the United States government to commit itself, through ratification of four United Nations conventions (dealing with Genocide, Slavery, Forced Labor and the Political Rights of Women), to the building and strengthening of a body of international law in the field of human rights. The first such measure, concerned with the basic, inviolable right to life itself, was the Genocide Convention. Developed in the highly charged atmosphere of the years immediately following the Holocaust, it was adopted unanimously by the UN General Assembly in 1948 and signed, but never ratified, by the United States. The Committee’s task was to overcome legislators’ resistance to ratification, through direct lobbying, publicity campaigns and outreach to sympathetic sectors of the U.S. population. Under the leadership of its Executive Secretary, Betty Kaye Taylor (a long-time staff member of the Jewish Labor Committee) the Committee mobilized labor, civil rights, civil liberties, religious and fraternal organizations, and achieved a steadily growing body of support from Democratic and liberal Republican senators. But Congressional opposition and public indifference proved intransigent. The campaign was to last much longer, and was strewn with more bitter disappointments, than the organizers of the Committee could have imagined; ratification was finally achieved in 1986. The collection includes administrative records, publicity materials, reports, clippings, articles, and extensive correspondence with prominent supporters of ratification. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Ad Hoc Committee on the Human Rights and Genocide Treaties.
Box 1-6
Provenance
The records were donated to the Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by the Jewish Labor Committee and Betty Kaye Taylor in 1996.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Ad Committee on the Human Rights and Genocide Treaties was organized in the spring of 1964 by some 35 national voluntary organizations for the purpose of encouraging the United States government to commit itself, through ratification of four United Nations conventions (dealing with Genocide, Slavery, Forced Labor and the Political Rights of Women), to the building and strengthening of a body of international law in the field of human rights. The first such measure, concerned with the basic, inviolable right to life itself, was the Genocide Convention. Developed in the highly charged atmosphere of the years immediately following the Holocaust, it was adopted unanimously by the UN General Assembly in 1948 and signed, but never ratified, by the United States. Despite President John F. Kennedy’s support for ratification of all four conventions, expressed in addresses to the U.S. Senate and the UN General Assembly in the summer and fall of 1963, Congressional resistance to ratification proved to be deeply entrenched. The Committee’s task was to overcome that resistance, through direct lobbying, publicity campaigns and outreach to sympathetic sectors of the U.S. population. The campaign was to last much longer, and was strewn with more bitter disappointments, than the organizers of the Committee could have imagined.
The organizations comprising the Ad Hoc Committee represented a wide range of civil liberties, religious, labor and fraternal groups, among them the American Civil Liberties Union, the American Friends Service Committee, the American Veterans Committee, B’nai B’rith, Hadassah, the Industrial Union Department of the AFL-CIO, the Jewish Labor Committee, the NAACP, the National Conference of Christians and Jews, the United Church of Christ, the Women’s International League for Peace and Freedom, the Workmen’s Circle, the Ukrainian National Association and several individual trade unions. Through the National Conference of Christians and Jews the Committee forged close ties with the social action wings of a number of Christian and Jewish denominations. The United Nations Association put the Committee in touch with liberal supporters of the UN nationwide, and by using its connections to the AFL-CIO and the Jewish Labor Committee the Committee garnered support throughout the labor movement.
The day-to-day work of the Committee was coordinated by its able Executive Secretary, Betty Kaye Taylor. Born in Freeport, Long Island, Betty Kaye attended Freeport High School and the Morris High School in the Bronx. She graduated from the University of Wisconsin in 1946 and went to work as an organizer, based in Chicago, for the International Ladies’ Garment Workers Union. Beginning in her high-school years she had been a political activist as a member of the Young People’s Socialist League, and was eventually recommended by Daniel Bell to become an employee of the Jewish Labor Committee. She worked with JLC staffer (and Warsaw Ghetto survivor) Jerzy Glicksman in Chicago and transferred to the JLC’s national office in New York in 1948. There she coordinated the work of the JLC’s field representatives, edited Labor Reports (a JLC news service) and later became an assistant to the National Director. Bette Kaye Taylor remained on the JLC staff during her years of service to the Ad Hoc Committee. When she retired from the JLC in 1981, the work of the Committee was carried on by Hyman Bookbinder of the American Jewish Committee. Throughout the life of the Committee its work was greatly assisted by William Korey, foreign affairs director of B’nai B’rith and a leading scholar in the field of international human rights.
In the course of its years of work, the Committee won the support of an impressive roster of prominent individuals, in and out of Congress. But its efforts met a long string of defeats. Although President Truman had urged ratification of the convention, xenophobia, isolationism, public indifference and the exigencies of superpower politics proved to be insuperable obstacles during four decades of Democratic and Republican administrations alike. In 1967 the Committee’s staunchest Congressional champion, Senator William Proxmire, delivered the first of innumerable speeches (sometimes daily statements) on the subject over the next twenty years. Throughout the horrors of Biafra, East Pakistan and Rwanda, the Senate continued to turn a deaf ear. After the Khmer Rouge atrocities in Cambodia became public several senators joined the battle for ratification, still to no avail. Ironically, as historian Brian Urquhart has pointed out (NY Review of Books, April 25, 2002, p.13), it was in the wake of the public relations disaster of President Ronald Reagan’s visit to the SS graves at Bitburg, Germany, that the treaty was finally ratified. Even this gesture of concession to public outrage was undermined by a number of provisions immunizing the U.S. against the possibility of ever being charged with genocide. The vote in the Senate was 83 in favor, 11 against and 6 not voting; the U.S. was the 98th country to ratify the convention.
Sources:
William Korey, “The United States and the Genocide Convention: Leading Advocate and Leading Obstacle,” Ethics and International Affairs, Vol. 11 (1997), pp. 271-290.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes administrative records of the Ad Hoc Committee (reports, financial records, internal correspondence, etc.) as well as a comprehensive collection of the outreach and publicity materials generated during the campaign for U.S. ratification of the Genocide and other UN conventions (flyers, conference programs, mass mailings, magazine articles, clippings, statements from the Congressional record, etc.). The collection also includes numerous resolutions passed by member organizations in support of the campaign and polls of Congressional opinion on the issue.
Notable individuals represented in files of correspondence with supporters of the Committee’s work are Presidents John F. Kennedy, Lyndon Johnson and Jimmy Carter, Senator William Proxmire, Senator Hubert H. Humphrey, Senator J. William Fulbright, Senator Jacob K. Javits, Senator Edward M Kennedy, Arthur J. Goldberg, William Korey, David Dubinsky, Herschel Halbert, Telford Taylor and Martin Luther King, Jr., among others.
NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Organized into 1 series:
I, General Files, 1943-1982.
Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide (1948).; Goldberg, Arthur J.; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.).; Korey, William, 1922-2009; National Council of Christians and Jews.; Proxmire, William.; Taylor, Betty Kaye; United Nations Association.; Clippings (information artifacts).; Correspondence.; Fliers (printed matter); Genocide |x Political aspects.; Genocide |z United States |x Public opinion.; Genocide.; Human rights.; New York (N.Y.); Press releases.; Reports.
- Series I: General Files, 1943-1984.
  - Abraham, Morris, 1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Actions of Member Organizations, 1971-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ad Hoc Committee, 1970-1974, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Advisory Committee, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Executive Board, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Finances, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Fundraising, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Mailings, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Member Organizations, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Minutes, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Minutes, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Ad Hoc Committee: Statement of Purpose, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Advisory Committee Meeting, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - AFL-CIO, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - AFL-CIO: Resolutions, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - AFL-CIO: Statements, 1964, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - AFL-CIO: Survey, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - American Bar Association, 1950, 1963-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - American Bar Association: Resolution, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Ethical Union, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - American Jewish Committee, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - American Jewish Congress, 1963-1967, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - American Veterans Committee, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Armenians, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Assembly for Human Rights (Montreal), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bagby, Grover C.: Article, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Baldwin, Roger, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Baptist Church, 1967, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bibliographies, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bipartisan Appeal, 1971-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bitker, Bruno V., 1963-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - B’nai B’rith, 1964-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bookbinder, Hyman, 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Boston, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Britain, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brooke, Edward W., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Buckley, James: Petition to, 1971-1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Canada, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Carter, Pres. Jimmy, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Catholic Association for International Peace, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Catholic Church, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Church, Frank, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Church Amendments, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cleveland, Harlan, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Conference of Presidents, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Conference (Washington), 1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Conference (Washington), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Conference (Washington), 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Conference (Washington): Delegates’ Packet, 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Conference (Washington): Preparations, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Congressional Committee on Foreign Affairs, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Congressional Record: Senate, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Congressional Record: Senate, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Contributions, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1964-Sep 1964 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, Oct 1964-Dec 1964 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1965-May 1965 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, Jun 1965-Dec 1965 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Crank Mail, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Democratic National Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Democratic Party, 1964, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Detroit, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Dodd, Thomas, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Draft Resolution: International Human Rights and Genocide Convention, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Dubinsky, David, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Dworkis, Martin, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Elendorf Meeting, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Emma Lazarus Clubs, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Episcopal Church, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ervin, Sam J., 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ferwerda, Vernon, 1971-1980 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Finances, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Foreign Policy Association, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Fulbright, J. William, 1964, 1968-1979 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Gardner, Richard N., 1965-1967, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Genocide: General, 1943, 1952-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Genocide Convention: General, 1949, 1964-1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Genocide Convention and Radical Right, 1970-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Genocide Convention: Women’s Appeal, 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Genocide Mailings, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Genocide: Poison Gas (Washington Post), 1971 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Goldberg, Arthur J., 1966-1979 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Goldberg Letter to Senators, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Gordon, Richard, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Halbert, Herschel, 1967-1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Halpern, Seymour, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Helsinki, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Hesburgh, Fr. Theodore, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Human Rights: General, 1963-1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Human Rights and Genocide Packet, 1964-1966, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Human Rights: International Conventions and Covenants, 1967, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Human Rights: Internet, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Human Rights: Pamphlets, 1963-1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Human Rights: Policy Statements, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Human Rights Year, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Human Rights Year: Booklets, 1963-1968 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - ICFTU Statement, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Inquiries/Orders, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Institute for International Order, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - International Bill of Human Rights, [1977], undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - International Convention on the Elimination…of Racial Discrimination, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - International League for the Rights of Man, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - International Rescue Committee, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Javits, Jacob K., 1965, 1973-1979 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Javits-Proxmire Letter, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Jewish Community Relations Councils, 1971-1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Jewish Labor Committee, 1963-1970, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Jewish Labor Committee: on Genocide, 1950-1967 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Jewish Labor Committee: Soviet Jewry, 1949-1970 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Jewish Organizations: on Ratification, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Jewish Organizations: on Ratification, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Johnson, Pres. Lyndon B., 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Judaism in Social Action, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Kampelman, Max, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Kennedy, Edward M., 1973 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Kennedy, Pres. John F., 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Kennedy, Robert F., 1964 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1966 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Korey, William, 1964-1979 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Kotler, Arnold H.: “US and Human Rights Conventions”, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Leadership Conference on Human Rights, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Liskofsky, Sidney, 1963-1966, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Mansfield, Mike, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Methodist Church, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Michigan Ad Hoc Committee, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Middle East, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Minnesota, 1963, 1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Minnesota, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Minnesota Labor Committee for Human Rights, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Morse, Arthur D., 1970 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - NAACP, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - National Citizens Commission on International Cooperation, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - National Community Relations Advisory Council, 1949, 1963-1967, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, 1972-1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - National Conference on Human Rights, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - National Council of Jewish Women, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - National Freedom Assembly, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - National Lawyers Guild, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - National Urban League, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - New York Times Coverage, 1964-1972 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Nixon, Pres. Richard M., 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Nixon: Letter to Genocide Conference, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - “No Auspices” Meeting, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Opposition, 1965-1978 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Orders for Material, undated, 1971-1981 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Pacem in Terris, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Philadelphia, 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - President’s Commission for the Observance of Human Rights Year, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Press Coverage, 1960s, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Press Coverage, 1970s, 1982, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Press Releases, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Proxmire, William, 1971-1982 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Proxmire, William: Congressional Record, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Publicity Material, 1959-1970 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Quaker Program at the UN, 1964-1967 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Ratification: Charts, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Ratification: General, 1965-1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Ratification of Conventions, 1967-1970, undated (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - “Ratification of Human Rights Conventions,” paper by Diane La Voy, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Religious Organizations, 1972-1980 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Republican Party, 1964, undated (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Resolutions, 1953-1981, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Rights of Women, undated (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Robinson, Nehemiah: “The Genocide Convention”, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson A., 1968 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - San Francisco, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Seaman, Bernard, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Seminar on Human Rights: Confidential Report, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Senate Appeals, 1970-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Senate Correspondence, 1964-1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Senate Correspondence, 1966-1968, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Senate Correspondence, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1963-1968 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1971-1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee: Abram Testimony, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Senate Foreign Relations Committee: Correspondence, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Senate: Letters (Samples), 1972, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Senate: Poll, 1965-1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Senate: Poll, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Senate: Questionnaire, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Senators’ Statements, 1965-1974, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Socialist Party, USA, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Soviet Union, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Speeches for Senators, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Statement on Genocide Convention, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Statements and Resolutions, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Suggested Guidelines for Community Action, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Survey of Senate (AJC), 1970 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Taylor, Betty Kaye, 1977-1978 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Taylor, Betty Kaye: Oral History conducted by Mildred Finger, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 19a)
  - Taylor, Telford, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Tillett, Gladys A., 1966 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Trade Unions, 1971-1979, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Unitarian Universalist Association, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - United Nations, 1949, 1964-1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - United Nations Association, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - United Nations Association, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - United Nations Association, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - United Nations Association, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - United Nations Association, 1972-1979 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - UN Commission on Human Rights, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - UN Convention on Forced Labor, 1957, 1963, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - UN Convention on Political Rights of Women, 1967, undated (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - UN Convention on Racial Discrimination, 1965-1966, undated (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - UN Convention on Slavery, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - UN Genocide Convention: Background, 1967, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - United Nations: Ratifying States, 1968, 1972-1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - UN: Washington Seminar on Human Rights, 1967-1979 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - U.S. State Department, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - United World Federalists, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Universal Declaration of Human Rights, 1968-1978 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Visits to Senators, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Warren, Earl: Statement, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Washington Conference, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Women’s Appeal, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Workmen’s Circle, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - World Assembly for Human Rights, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - World Jewish Congress, 1964-1968 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - World Federalist Youth, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 48)